<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20031101//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.1/archivearticle.dtd">
<article>
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">IJAR2</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Indian Journal of Agricultural Research</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0367-8245</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">0976-058X</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Agricultural Research Communication Centre</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="other">ijar2-54-2-017</article-id>
         <doi-group>
            <article-doi>
               <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                         ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18805/IJARe.A-467">10.18805/IJARe.A-467</ext-link>
            </article-doi>
         </doi-group>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Research Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Impact of UV Irradiation of Winter Wheat Seeds on Enzymatic Activity in the Germination Period</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Simonova</surname>
                  <given-names>E.N.</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Ayrapetyan</surname>
                  <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
               </name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Eroshenko</surname>
                  <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                  <sup>2</sup>
               </xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Vertiy</surname>
                  <given-names>N.S.</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                  <sup>1</sup>
               </xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff>
            <deptname>Department of Technology and Commodity Science</deptname>, <instname>Federal State Budget Educational Institution of Higher Education</instname>, <instparent>K.G. Razumovsky Moscow State University of Technologies and Management, (the First Cossack University)</instparent>, <instcity>Moscow</instcity>, <instcountry>Russia</instcountry>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
            <deptname>Department of Biotechnology and Chemistry</deptname>, <instname>Federal State Budget Educational Institution of Higher Education</instname>, <instparent>K.G. Razumovsky Moscow State University of Technologies and Management (the First Cossack University)</instparent>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
            <deptname>Department of Food Technology and Equipment</deptname>, <instname>Federal State Budget Educational Institution of Higher Education</instname>, <instparent>K.G. Razumovsky Moscow State University of Technologies and Management (the First Cossack University)</instparent>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="cor001">*Corresponding Author: E.N. Simonova, <deptname>Department of Technology and Commodity Science</deptname>, <instname>Federal State Budget Educational Institution of Higher Education</instname>, <instparent>K.G. Razumovsky Moscow State University of Technologies and Management, (the First Cossack University)</instparent>, <instcity>Moscow</instcity>, <instcountry>Russia</instcountry>. Email: <email>e.n.simonova@mail.ru</email>
            </corresp>
            <fn>
               <p>
                  <bold>Online published on 23 May, 2020</bold>.</p>
            </fn>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>54</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <fpage>232</fpage>
         <lpage>236</lpage>
         <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>There have been conducted comprehensive studies of the effect of UV irradiation on enzymatic activity in the germination period of winter wheat seeds under different irradiation regimes. They have identified the maximum increase in amylase activity on the fourth day from the beginning of seed germination in variants with three and five minute UV irradiation and this indicator's value exceeded that of the control variant on 58.6% and 64.1%, respectively. Catalase activity was of its maximum value by the fourth day from the beginning of seed germination in variants with three and five minute UV irradiation and exceeded the value of the control variant on 14.7% and 17.7%, respectively. Peroxidase activity was of its maximum on the eighth day from the beginning of seed germination in all experimental variants. In a variant with three minute UV irradiation, peroxidase activity exceeded the control values of this indicator on 50% and in a variant with five minute UV irradiation on 55%. The use of a mercury-quartz lamp BNPO 2-30-001U3.5 to stimulate physio-logical and biochemical processes in germinating seeds made it possible to identify different enzymatic activities depending on the time exposure to UV irradiation.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <title>Keywords</title>
            <kwd>Amylase</kwd>
            <kwd>Catalase</kwd>
            <kwd>Enzymes</kwd>
            <kwd>Peroxidase</kwd>
            <kwd>Ultraviolet irradiation</kwd>
            <kwd>Winter wheat</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="5"/>
         </counts>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <!--
<back>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
</ref-list>
</back>
-->
</article>
