<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20031101//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.1/archivearticle.dtd">
<article>
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">IJAR1</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Indian Journal of Animal Research</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0367-6722</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">0976-0555</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Agricultural Research Communication Centre</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="other">ijar1-54-3-018</article-id>
         <doi-group>
            <article-doi>
               <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                         ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18805/ijar.B-3766">10.18805/ijar.B-3766</ext-link>
            </article-doi>
         </doi-group>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Research Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Meloxicam induced toxicopathology studies in Wistar rats</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Bharani</surname>
                  <given-names>S. Pramod</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Naik</surname>
                  <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
               </name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Parija</surname>
                  <given-names>S.C.</given-names>
               </name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Panda</surname>
                  <given-names>S.K.</given-names>
               </name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff>
            <deptname>Department of Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology</deptname>, <instname>College of Veterinary Science and Animal Husbandry</instname>, <instparent>Odisha University of Agriculture and Technology</instparent>, <instcity>Bhubaneshwar</instcity>-<instpincode>751 003</instpincode>, <inststate>Orissa</inststate>, <instcountry>India</instcountry>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="cor001">*Corresponding Author: S. Pramod Bharani, <deptname>Department of Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology</deptname>, <instname>College of Veterinary Science and Animal Husbandry</instname>, <instparent>Odisha University of Agriculture and Technology</instparent>, <instcity>Bhubaneshwar</instcity>-<instpincode>751 003</instpincode>, <inststate>Orissa</inststate>, <instcountry>India</instcountry>. Email: <email>pbharanis@gmail.com</email>
            </corresp>
            <fn>
               <p>
                  <bold>Online published on 8 April, 2020</bold>.</p>
            </fn>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>54</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <fpage>363</fpage>
         <lpage>366</lpage>
         <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are the most commonly used class of drugs for treating inflammation and pain. Meloxicam has analgesic, anti-inflammatory and antipyretic properties and is a commonly used NSAID in veterinary practice. The present study was done to evaluate effect of meloxicam on toxico-pathological and hematological parameters in Wistar rats. Eighteen Wistar rats were equally divided into three groups i.e. Group I, Group II and Group III. Group I (negative control) rats received only Normal saline (0.9%) @ 1ml/kg. Group II (Low dose) received meloxicam@ 4 mg/kg B.W. and Group III (High dose) rats received <email>meloxicam@8</email> mg/kg B.W. orally by gavage for 28 days. Dose-dependent clinical signs and lesions were observed after meloxicam treatment. Kidneys and liver were severely hemorrhagic at the high dose, while intestine and stomach had ulcers and erosions. Hematological values were altered after 28 days of administration. Total Erythrocyte Count (TEC), Packed Cell Volume (PCV), Haemoglobin values were decreased and TLC count was significantly increased in both doses of meloxicam treated groups in a dosedependent manner. It was concluded that meloxicam caused GIT lesions, nephrotoxicity, hepatotoxicity and variation in the hematological parameters at selected dose and duration.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <title>Keywords</title>
            <kwd>Hepato-toxicity</kwd>
            <kwd>Meloxicam</kwd>
            <kwd>NSAID</kwd>
            <kwd>Nephrotoxicity</kwd>
            <kwd>Rats</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="4"/>
         </counts>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <!--
<back>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
</ref-list>
</back>
-->
</article>
