<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">IJAR2</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Indian Journal of Agricultural Research</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0367-8245</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0976-058X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Agricultural Research Communication Centre</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">ijar2-54-2-003</article-id>
      <doi-group>
        <article-doi>
          <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18805/IJARe.5369">10.18805/IJARe.5369</ext-link>
        </article-doi>
      </doi-group>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pollen Substitute Diet for Apis <italic>Mellifera</italic>: Consumption and Effects on Colony Parameters in Sub-Tropical Himalaya</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumari</surname>
            <given-names>Indu</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Rajesh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>
        <deptname>Department of Life Science</deptname>, <instname>School of Basic Sciences</instname>, <instparent>Arni University</instparent>, <instcity>Kangra</instcity>-<instpincode>176 401</instpincode>, <inststate>Himachal Pradesh</inststate>, <instcountry>India</instcountry></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor001">*Corresponding Author: Rajesh Kumar, <deptname>Department of Life Science</deptname>, <instname>School of Basic Sciences</instname>, <instparent>Arni University</instparent>, <instcity>Kangra</instcity>-<instpincode>176401</instpincode>, <inststate>Himachal Pradesh</inststate>, <instcountry>India</instcountry>. Email: <email>drkumar83@rediffmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn>
          <p>
            <bold>Online published on 23 May, 2020</bold>.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>54</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>147</fpage>
      <lpage>153</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Apiculture plays an important role in improving crop productivity all over the world. The enrichment and enhancement of apiculture lies in the good health and hygiene of honey bees. Honeybees require pollen and nectar rich flowers to satisfy their nutritional requirements. But such flowers of bee's interest are not available round the year. Therefore, honey bees require special care and management during dearth periods. The palatability, consumption and effects of protein-rich diet(s) were assessed on honey bee colonies of <italic>Apis mellifera.</italic> The colonies were also supplied with patties of diet formulated in laboratory (bee sup), diet proposed by Haydak (1967) and NBB, New Delhi (India), sugar syrup and no supplementary feed as control. Feeding trials were carried out during May to July 2017 and 2018, using 24 equalized experimental colonies receiving diet formulations for 8 weeks. The feed consumption for bee-sup was higher than Haydak's diet during both the years. Significant differences were recorded for various colony attributes viz. sealed brood, unsealed brood, bee population, bee covered frames and honey production in the colonies provided bee-sup in comparison to Haydak's diet, sugar syrup and control colonies. The results indicate the potential of bee-sup for improving strength, health and build up of colonies during dearth periods.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Artificial diet</kwd>
        <kwd>Bees</kwd>
        <kwd>Brood</kwd>
        <kwd>Dearth period</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="7" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <!--
<back>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
</ref-list>
</back>
-->
</article>